Nicholas Spyrison

Visualization, Analysis, & Machine Learning

Parker, CO 80134 (720) 571-8555 nspyrison.netlify.com/ github.com/nspyrison in linkedin.com/in/nspyrison/

Summary

I am a published data scientist with more than 5 years of clean, analyzing, and visualizing semi-structured data. I have a passion for using data visualization to lead analysis, and abstract away the mental work allowing the audience to focus on the evidence on hand.

Employment History

06/2022 – now **Research Data Scientist**, *University of Queensland*,

Clayton, VIC.

- o R, python, Git
- o Ad-hoc analysis and visualization of global COVID19 health record data, we published on kidney health outcomes stratified by social-economic status
- Exploration, Multiple imputation, sparse and dense machine learning modeling, and hyperparameter tuning on relational database of COVID19 health record

07/2018 – 06/2022 **Data Fluency Instructor**, *Monash University*,

Clayton, VIC.

- o R, python, Git, PowerBI, Rest API
- o Data Fluency Instructor: Lead workshops (10-30p) on R, modeling, PowerBI, & Git
- Teaching Assistant: Postgraduate data exploration & visualization | business & economic statistics.
- Research Officer: census & text data; wrangling, analysis, & reporting

12/2016 - 1/2018Business Intelligence Developer, CPI Card Group, Denver, CO.

- SQL, SSRS, Crystal, Oracle BICS (cloud), Excel
- Database reporting; across 4 reporting platforms and 4 database instances
- Developed supply chain report tracking a cost reduction of more than \$4M USD

07/2015 - 10/2016 Business Intelligence Developer, UDR Real Estate Investment Trust, Denver, CO.

- SQL, SSRS, agile, SSAS/OLAP/MOLAP, WebFOCUS
- Responsible for transitioning reports from WebFOCUS to SSRS
- On-call for enterprise-wide ETL process

11/2014 – 04/2015 Business Intelligence Analyst, Heartland Financial USA,

Dubuque, IA.

o SQL, WebFOCUS financial reporting

02/2013 - 05/2014 **Delivery Analyst**, *IBM - International Business Machines*,

Dubuque, IA.

- o R, Excel, VBA reporting to teams and management
- Step-wise model selection with dozens of variables
- ETL scripting via VBA macros for about 0.5 FTE savings across the team
- IBM's lean/six sigma green belt, root cause analysis (RCA)

01/2010 – 08/2012 **Laboratory Technician**, The Ames Laboratory & Iowa State University, Ames, IA, Superconductivity & Magnetism Low-temperature Laboratory.

Conduct cryogenic material characterization, analysis, and publication

Authored Software (R Packages)

09/2022 **cheem** – Novel analysis and interactive visual for exploring ML interpretability

10/2020 spinifex - ggplot2-like API for composing & exporting animated projections <u>Link</u> Link

Education

02/2018 - 06/2022 Ph.D. Information Technology & Statistics, Monash University, Clayton, VIC, Dimension reduction, interactive and animated data visualization, machine learning Thesis: Interactive and Dynamic Visualization of High-dimensional Data. o Fit random forest models on several contemporary datasets also shown to generalize to other models with SVM and XGboost. o Utilized SHAP and LIME local explanations to explore local linear variable importance to understand large residuals in the models Created novel animated and interactive visuals facilitating this exploration in a shiny app Authored an R package hosted on CRAN to facilitate understanding and adoption 08/2008 – 05/2012 B.Sc. Statistics, *Iowa State University*, minors in Physics and Mathematics, Ames, IA. Skills Specialization Data visualization, dimension reduction, machine learning, interpretability Programs R, SQL, Python, Git, GitHub, Excel, VBA Packages ggplot2, tidyverse, plotly, shiny, tidymodels, caret, keras, pandas, scikit-learn Models Random forest, xgboost, neural networks, SVM, logistic regression, parameter tuning Reporting SSRS, Tableau, PowerBI, Rmarkdown, Shiny Awards and Honors 06/2022 Invited article for INFORM's OR/MS Tomorrow <u>Link</u> 04/2022 RStudio: March "Top 40" New CRAN Packages Link 05/2022 Monash Postgraduate Publication Award 10/2020 Melbourne Datathon 2020 - 1st place of several hundred entries Link Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions 11/2018 ACEMS Impact and Engagement Award 07/2018 UseR2018 Datathon – 3rd place Spatio temporal animated visualization of over 7 million avian sightings 2018 – 2022 Faculty Graduate Research Scholarship 2018 – 2022 Co-funded Monash Graduate Scholarship

References and publications available on request.

05/2012 Nominated for Student Employee of the Year 05/2011 Nominated for Student Employee of the Year

05/2008 American Legion Award